hey what's up guys My Name Is AO and
welcome back to my C++ Series today
we're going to be talking all about
classes in C++ so we're finally getting
into something called objectoriented
programming which is a very popular way
of programming object-oriented
programming is really just a style that
you can adopt as to how you write your
code other languages such as C and Java
are primarily objectoriented languages
in fact you can't really write any other
type of code I mean you can if you
really really try but ultimately those
languages are meant to be OB on to
languages however C++ is something a
little bit different because it doesn't
really enforce a certain style upon you
the language C for example doesn't
actually support object AR programming
because in order to have object AR
programming you need to be able to have
Concepts such as classes and objects and
that's not something that's available in
C however C++ does add all of that
functionality if you wish to use it and
it is almost always a good idea to use
it to some extent so we're going to be
talking about what classes are in this
video to put it simply classes are just
a way to group data and or
functionality together for example think
of a game in a game we might want to
have some kind of representation of a
player so what kind of things do we need
to actually represent a player we
definitely want some kind of data for
example the position of the player in
our game World certain attributes that
the player might possess such as the
speed at which the player moves we might
also want to have some kind of 3D model
that represents the player on the screen
all of this data needs to be stored
somewhere we could go ahead and create
variables for all this in in fact let's
go ahead and take a look at what that
would look like let's say that we want
to make a player here in our code we
might want to have a position so I'll
just say X and Y and then potentially a
speed let's just set the speed equal to
two so these are all integers for now
you can probably start to see that this
is getting a little bit messy and in
fact because these names are so generic
you might want to do something like
player X player Y for the X and Y
coordinate of the player maybe player
speed and this really does start to get
a little bit messy especially if we
decide actually we want two plays in our
game well then suddenly you're going to
have to duplicate this and start doing
something like player x0 player X1
instead of this you could of course use
an array but the point is still the same
it's just kind of a bunch of variables
that aren't grouped together they're
just unorganized they're just sitting in
our code and it's just not a good idea
another great example of why this is
annoying is because if I want to write a
function that moves the player or
something like that I suddenly need to
be specifying all three parameters as
integers so for for example the x
coordinate the y coordinate the speed
all of this just becomes so much code
and so difficult to maintain and follow
that it's just it's really really messy
so what we can do instead is simplify
this by using a class we can create a
class for the player we can call it
player which contains all of that data
that we want all those variables kind of
in one type so instead of this let's
create a class called
player we do so by just using the word
class and then giving it a name this has
to be a unique name because cuz classes
are types we're basically creating a new
variable type and then we open and close
curly brackets as if this was a function
however note that we do actually need a
semicolon at the end of the closing
brace inside here we can specify all of
those variables that we did below for
example X and Y for the
position and then a speed variable as
well all right great so there we go
we've created a brand new class called
player which is essentially its own type
so if we were to start using this player
class we can create it as if it was any
other variable we write the typee so
player and then we give it any name I'm
going to call this player and that's it
we've created a new variable called
player which has the type player and of
course the definition of that type is
over here variables that are made from
class types are called objects and a new
object variable is called an instance so
what we've done here is we've
instantiated a player object because
we've created a new instance of that
player type now if we want to set those
variables we can simply write player Dot
and then the variable name such as X and
then assign it equal to something like
five if we try and compile this code
right now we're actually going to get an
error that tells us that player cannot
access private member declared in class
player this is because of something
called visibility when you create a new
class you have the option to specify how
visible the stuff in that class actually
is by default a class makes everything
private which means that only functions
inside that class can actually access
those variables however we want to be
able to access these variables from the
main function so what we actually need
to do is come up here and make it public
public means that we're allowed to
access access these variables outside of
this class anywhere in our code really
we'll talk a lot more about visibility
in a future video I don't really want to
get into it right now so you can see if
we compile our code here then our code
compile successfully okay pretty sweet
so we've achieved our first goal we've
managed to drastically clean up the code
and have all of our variables in one
place because really this collection of
variables represents a player so we've
managed to group it nicely now that
we've got all this data suppose that we
actually want our player to do something
for example move somewhere so we need to
write a function which changes the
player's X and Y variables how can we do
that well we could write it as just a
standalone function so I'll write void
I'll call it move and then I would need
to take in the player that I would like
to move now we'll have to pass this by
reference because we'll actually be
modifying the player object and then
I'll also take in XA and ya which will
be the amount that we move the player by
in both X and Y then all I need to do is
just say playerx plus = XA and player. Y
plus = y a we can also use that speed
variable that we have there by
multiplying our amount by the speed all
right pretty cool and if we wanted to
call that we would just write move
player and then by how much we want to
move the player so maybe 1 - one and
there we go we've written a function
that can move the player however we can
do a little bit better than this earlier
I said that classes can actually contain
functionality so what that basically
means is that we can move that move
function of ours into the class and
functions inside classes are called
Methods so I can literally go over here
into my code and just move this a little
bit up so that it's inside the player
class and there we go now obviously
we're in inside the player class now so
we actually have access to these
variables we don't need to pass a player
object in because we're already inside a
player object so if I get rid of this
and then all of these the X and Y and
speed that we're referring to will be
the current objects variables if I come
down over here I can change my code now
to just say player. move and there we go
we've simplified our code quite a bit
every player object is going to have its
own move function and when we call move
for that specific player object that is
the player object that will move again
this isn't really any different to
having the move function outside of the
player class all it does is it kind of
cleans up our code and makes everything
look a little bit nicer and that's a
huge bonus when you're dealing with a
lot of code because the more code you
have the more complicated it can get and
the harder it can actually become to
maintain that code so having things like
this to keep your code cleaner is
actually a very very welcome thing so
that's it that is essentially the basics
of what classes are classes allow us to
group variables together into a Time
and also add functionality to those
variables because if you take a look at
this code one more time what we've
really done is we've just defined three
variables that kind of exist in one type
and also a function which manipulates
those variables that's really all we've
done of course that function can do
literally anything but the gist of it is
we've got data and functions to
manipulate that data and that's really
all the class is now there are so many
uses for classes and we'll kind of start
getting into them in the future this is
also literally just a basics of what a
class is there is so many more things we
can do with classes which is why the
next few videos are going to be taking a
look at those things in more detail also
I want you to keep in mind that whilst
classes are extremely useful and can
keep your code a lot cleaner they can't
do anything that you can't do without
classes classes don't give you any kind
of new functionality that you could not
have done otherwise anything you can do
with classes you can actually do without
classes which is why languages such as C
exist and are perfectly usable languages
they don't have classes and yet we can
still write code classes are just there
to make our lives easier as programmers
they're essentially just syntactic sugar
that we can use to organize our code and
make it easier to maintain that's all
that they are anyway I hope you guys
enjoyed this video if you did please hit
that like button you can also follow me
on Twitter and Instagram and of course
next time we'll be taking a look at this
stuff in more detail and seeing just
what we can do with it
[Music]
goodbye